hello I'm your host David Barnard
today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in Revenue
cat state of subscription apps report
each episode this series will explore
one crucial metric and share actionable
insights from Top subscription app
operators with me today Lucas level VP
of product at paddle on the podcast I
talk with Lucas about maximizing success
with web subscriptions how web payment
flexibility enables better user
experiences
and why making it hard to cancel can
ultimately hurt your business more than
it helps hey Lucas thanks so much for
joining me on the podcast today thanks
very much for having me David looking
forward to it so this is the first year
Revenue cat has ever worked with
Partners to include additional data in
the stateus subscription apps report and
I actually have not looked at this data
yet but paddle has shared some web data
that will be in the report and so I
didn't want to talk through the data
today but I know you personally and the
paddle team work with a ton of apps on
web to app and you know being successful
on web payments outside of the app
stores so let's just kick it off with
some of the top recommendations and what
you see working on the web for
subscription apps yeah sure sure so I
guess from our vantage point we're
really excited about web to app so
paddle is an endtoend billing and
payments platform on the web and we're
working with lots of mobile app
companies on their web Revenue channels
and how to best deploy them and we've
seen as you pointed out and some of this
data will be shared in the report a big
increase in mobile app companies who are
looking at the web as an opportunity to
acquire customers yeah I I feel like
that's all I've been hearing about the
last two or three years is like web web
web like how do we get web on boring
working and yeah yeah I think it's
really interesting I think there are
some key reasons why that's happening
and I won't I won't sort of bore on with
that around sort of attribution and
perhaps some gross margin efficiency
around cost but I think a lot of people
are coming to the web and realizing that
there are actually other advantages to
the web around expanding your audience
types being able to reach users who are
more present on the web and might not be
searching for apps in the App Store and
also leveraging a lot of the a lot of
the billing flexibility that you get on
the web so web billing has been around
for a long time and it can provide a
bunch of flexibility and tooling that
you can use to your advantage on the web
which I think is really interesting so
the way I think about it is very much
it's not just a cost-saving opportunity
it's actually a growth opportunity
there's a lot opportunity on the web in
terms of deploying different billing
models and deploying different types of
pricing experimentation and AB testing
in a way that that you're a little bit
restricted with on the App Stores so I
think in terms of like how to best think
about it I think the starting point for
me would be thinking about like why
people will visit your website on the
web or how are people going to come to
you on the web we see companies who are
driving traffic to the web through
through content marketing and using
content marketing as a landing point and
then con converting users into sort of
paid users on the web and then pushing
them to the app there but we're also
seeing a lot of companies deploy web
funnels and I think especially for for
mobile apps that have quite a large
component of personalization we're
seeing web funnels be a really effective
way um of driving traffic to the web so
the classic categories there are health
and fitness we're seeing a lot of web
funnels in health and fitness education
as well so language learning apps um
Wellness apps who are all using that
effectively and an reducing the web
funnel off the back of a paid ad on a
social media platform for example and
seeing really good conversion rates and
then also good renewal rates as well on
those subscriptions too so a lot of
reasons to consider the web but I think
it's also how you build a really
effective web channel is very much
dependent on the type of mobile app that
you are and the type of customers or the
type of users that you're looking to
acquire yeah it does seem like and you
kind of alluded to it already is that
apps that do kind of have a higher
intent user coming in health and fitness
being something we talk about constantly
is that somebody looking to get fit and
or lose weight or or kind of these other
categories of of Health and Wellness
there's like a very strong deep personal
motivation to do those things and then
also a higher willingness to pay I mean
people are willing to pay a lot for
their health they may be spending 50 100
bucks a month on supplements and gym
memberships and it can easily add up to
hundreds of dollars a month so these
health and fitness apps are relative ly
inexpensive comparatively and then
education and other things I I think
there's a lot of categories where you do
see the web work better and then maybe
some categories where you don't any kind
of insights of where you've maybe seen
apps struggle and then any other
categories that you think have worked
especially well health and fitness is
working really well Wellness is working
well education and language learning is
working really well I think some areas
that where yet to see it really take off
and I probably wouldn't position this as
like these companies are struggling but
rather they haven't shown as much intent
yet is probably in like productivity is
a good example I think the lack of
personalization around how you use the
tool for example a notetaking tool or
something like this is not as
interesting I think when you're thinking
about a web funnel and building buying
intent through a web funnel so I think
that's an example media perhaps is
another example I don't have a lot of
sort of great examples around who it's
not working for I think it's more what
are the categories that are leading this
trend and I think there are other ways
in which those categories that perhaps
aren't investing in it as much to sort
of start thinking about it in the future
but at the moment it's very much the
apps with a high component of
personalization that are seeing really
really good results with web funnels
what are the things some of the things
that you see working really well you
keep talking about web funnels and you
know we've talked about this a lot on
the podcast in the past different forms
of onboarding different forms of kind of
like building up intent what are you
seeing working in that mobile app
companies that are thinking about the
journey end to end are seeing a lot of
good results
so thinking deeply about the web funnel
experience doing a lot of
experimentation on the pay wall and then
also taking that through to the checkout
as well are seeing great results on
conversion and I think companies that
are looking at those Journeys and really
thinking about how we can reduce
friction in that journey I seeing a lot
of success and also understanding the
routs that people are taking through the
web funnels and how they can produce a
buying signal and looking at that data
really carefully I think is good you
know we very much think about you know
your success of the on on the web if you
had to boil it down to two key data
points or two key numbers that matter
it's very much your conversion through
the funnel and your renewal at the end
of the first subscription cycle so how
many users get through the funnel and
convert based on a certain amount of AD
spend how many of those converted users
actually end up renewing it's easy to
get distracted by the former and not
think deeply about the latter and I
think the companies that are seeing a
lot of success are thinking really
deeply about retention and deploying
retention tooling and using things like
cancellation flows and downgrade flows
to reduce churn and to drive the renewal
rate in the right direction to really
boost and maximize the ROI of the web
Revenue channel that they're working on
so I do want to dive deeper into
retention here in a bit but before we do
that I wanted to talk a little bit about
some of what you just mentioned is that
there is so much more flexibility on the
web with how you charge the business
models and the ways you approach
monetization and and one of the things I
hear about constantly I've been
frustrated with the app store for years
is that they don't offer like per seat
licensing B2B is really hard if you have
a great b2c company and somebody comes
and says hey we want to buy 20 licenses
for all of our employees it's like
there's not really a great way to do
that on the App Store even like in a b
Toc sense where a employee wants to use
an app for work but they have a personal
App Store account it's like they would
have to like pay for it with their
personal credit card and then have this
whole like reimbursement process and so
the web does offer so much more
flexibility in business model and
monetization and how you do things what
are you seeing be successful there I
think it's interesting because to be
honest based on what we're seeing and
we're primarily working with bet C so
sort of consumer subscription apps at
the moment and most of them tend to be
deploying quite similar models on the
web as what they are on the app but we
are starting to see signs of some
companies sort of better understanding
the billing flexibility that the web
provides and starting to Tinker and play
with some different types of models to
be honest I think a lot of consumer apps
don't know what they don't know and so
there's definitely an education piece on
our part to sort of show them what's
possible on the web and support them in
exploring different pricing and
packaging scenarios and how they can
think about setting up their billing
models I also think we're going to go
further and further in this direction
because if you know if you look at Ai
and how AI is starting to be embedded
into different software products that's
really changing the way that we price as
well so a lot more consumption usage
based pricing tying pricing to the value
that you re see from a product as
opposed to it's a standard price
irrespective of how often you use it I
think we will start to see that roll
into the consumer side a little bit more
as consumers start to use more of these
products I think what we're seeing at
least from our vantage point is sort of
bringing over the Simplicity of the App
Store into the web we are seeing more
flexibility on the retention side I
think but I think from the billing model
and price model perspective I think
we've got a way to go before we see
mobile apps really start to challenge
some of those Norms that have been
ingrained in them based on some of the
restrictions in app store billing yeah I
mean that's part of the whole
conversation the last few years around
web is that it is this kind of whole new
opportunity that most apps aren't used
to working and so there is like this
kind of exploration phase and I agree I
mean I think we're just going to see a
lot more experimentation over time with
those different kind of pricing and
packaging and B2B opportunities
company building and stuff like that so
it's it's an interesting opportunity for
folks to be exploring even if you're not
seeing a ton of it yet the other thing I
do hear a lot about from a web billing
perspective is winb backs is that if
you're going to offer a discounted
subscription to try and win somebody
back a great way to do that is to go
ahead and send them to the web you know
it's a lot higher intent when you say
hey 50% off or 25% off if you go to the
web are you seeing those kind of things
to be successful we are yes we are we
are seeing quite a number of examples of
discounted pricing on the web and using
discounts of pricing in winback
campaigns as you mentioned we're even
seeing companies choose to offer
standard pricing at a lower rate on the
web just the counting for the fact that
you know the fee component is much
smaller on the web and choosing to pass
on some of those savings to the user I
think there are lots of companies that
are starting to double in that space and
I think consumers will start to pick up
on that and I've known Everyday People
sort of pick up on the fact that you
know purchasing X is cheaper on the web
than is on the app so I'm going to go
and do that or I'm going to cancel my
subscription on the app and resubscribe
on the web because of a cheaper price
there is some complexity around that
right around like when you can sort of
link from the App Store how you sort of
build those mechanisms but it's
definitely possible and something we're
definitely saying yeah and you know I
don't know that everybody's fully aware
of this cuz I still get questions almost
on a monthly basis from people like wait
can I actually send people to the web
and the basic answer answer is that you
cannot send people to the web from
inside the app although there's even
more flexibility now with both Apple and
Google with special entitlements where
you can actually in the apps into of the
web but then you still have to pay
commission it's all a bit complex but as
of I think about two two and a half
years ago there was a ruling I think it
was a the Japan Fair Trade Commission
that kind of pushed apple on this where
once you have somebody's contact
information if even if you collect it
with inside the app Apple tried for a
while like hey if you collect an email
inside of the app you can't then use
that email to send people to the web but
that's clearly very anti-competitive and
so they backed off on that and so any
contact information that you collect
within the app can be used to then push
people to the web so I've even seen apps
where if during that onboarding flow
inside the app they do collect an email
and the user doesn't immediately
subscribe then within minutes they're
pushing an email and and maybe it even
drops down as a notification while
they're still in your app saying hey
come to the web and save you know 30% or
40% or whatever that is I mean of course
Apple doesn't love that that happens but
like that is okay now like they cannot
and have stated in the rules that that
is okay so it can be a really powerful
tactic to nudge those users and using
email and text or other ways to do that
I think push notifications are still
under the rule of like that's kind of
technically in their ecosystem although
I do still see apps doing that on
occasion using push notifications
instead of email or text but yeah I
think a lot of people aren't aware of
just how much they can use even those
channels to push people to the web and
this is why we're seeing this is why
we're seeing especially in gaming a lot
more account creation so apps that
typically didn't require account
creation so you just in a game and you
just s just play the game and now asking
you to create an account put in your
name put in your email address for the
purpose of being able to retarget you in
different ways through other channels
that aren't directly the app it makes
sense in gaming right because you're
purchasing things on the fly so if
you're playing in an app and you're
purchasing Gems or tokens or swords or
whatever right ing game like like
in-game economy items and it's not just
a one-off purchase with a renewal at the
start there is a big drive to push them
to a web store to make those purchases
where they're offering bundled products
at discounted prices but to do that they
need to be a to contact you through
other means and so we're seeing a lot of
that through the the evolution of the
web store and gaming right the Epic game
store is a great example of a very
successful strategy that that is really
working for epic games and there are
other great examples of that as well but
yeah it's a brilliant point and you're
and your spot on yeah I mean I even saw
that I've played Pokémon go with my kids
for years now and I just got an email
like a few weeks ago of web exclusive
bundles that like really highlighted the
deals that you can get on the web for
Pokémon go so yeah I've been seeing it
more and more as well so I did want to
transition and start talking a little
bit more about retention and turn
mitigation on the web I think it's no
secret that some of the reason some apps
do see better retention on the web is
that it is just harder to cancel and I
mean famously you know New York Times
and others have made you call to cancel
if you have a web subscription and it is
it is way easier to cancel on the app
stores and so some of the boosts that
you're going to see on the web is just
people it's it's daunting I'm going to
have to go log in I'm going to have to
dig through settings and find a way to
cancel but ultimately like you're not
going to build a great business on
people you not being able to cancel
preventing them from canceling you know
those are the people are going to be
frustrated with your brand they're going
to be telling your friends not to
subscribe because they had a hard time
unsubscribing and so to build a great
business you don't want to put huge
barriers in the way of cancelling you
know you want users to be engaged with
the app and actually getting value so
what what are some of the ways that
you've seen the web work well for
retaining users and doing so in a way
that actually is like consumer friendly
I think this is really important and and
I actually agree with you like you can't
build a sustainable business on dark ux
patterns right we see that on both sides
we don't just see that on the
cancellation side you do see that up
front as well in at the pay wall around
like transparency around pricing right
because the web is much more flexible
you're not sort of under the guys of a
governance structure like apple well you
can push boundaries around that sort of
thing mislead consumers in certain ways
and there's just no way you're going to
build a sustainable business out of that
so like we would never ever encourage
that the part that is perhaps different
on the web is tooling available to you
in order to prevent churn there are a
number of examples of this and I think
your point about like the ftc's new
click to cancel rule is spot on and on
the web companies need to be really
aware of that there are options for you
so when someone clicks a cancel button
and it might be a one-click cancel
button but you can present a
cancellation flow which can ask some
questions about why are they canceling
and present some alternative options you
can build ways to trigger a downgrade
flow or a pause flow instead of a cancel
flow which means you might be
downgrading them from one plan to
another but you're not losing them
entirely you can also deploy
reactivations and winback campaigns in
different ways on the web which I think
is really interesting as well so I think
the web just gives you more flexibility
around some of the customization you can
build into your flows to either mitigate
CH in the first place or when churn is
happening perhaps get a better result
than you might have been able to get on
the app store and to your point I think
there's an opportunity on the web too to
create better experiences than you get
on the App Store like yeah it's super
easy to just go cancel on the App Store
and that is a good consumer experience
like feeling like you have control over
the subscription but with like being
able to pause being able to refund being
able to offer more flexibility to
customers on the web I do think can
actually create better customer
experiences you know one thing I've I've
heard from people that that's actually
working pretty well is instead of a free
trial offering a 30-day money back
guarantees like you can't do that on the
App Store you can't offer a money back
guarantee you can't automatically like
refund somebody so as an app developer
you can create better experiences on the
web through that flexibility where you
are driving that retention and helping
people stay retained but then offering
these best better experiences on the web
and I I think that's it's a huge
opportunity and kind of like we were
discussing earlier as kind of a for app
developers anyway a new thing that's
that's really been growing a lot the
past few years I think there's still a
ton to explore there absolutely it's
really exciting really exciting lots of
opportunity as you said like I think on
both stages in the funnel like the two
most important things as I said earlier
it's conversion through the pay wall and
the checkout and then keeping and
holding on to that customer and I think
at both of those points in the user
Journey the web is giving you
opportunity and flexibility and tooling
to do things that you are unable to do
in the App Store and and and that's the
unlock that people are realizing when
they come to the web they're coming for
the fees and staying for the flexibility
in a way right it's the catalyst is sort
of better attribution and lower cost
transaction fees but they get here and
they go wow I have all of this
flexibility around me I can do different
things I can experiment in different
ways I can I can try and build different
customer experiences to support my users
on their journey to keep them to engage
them and I think we'll continue to see
as web to app keeps evolving we'll
continue to see mobile app companies
push some of these boundaries explore
what's possible and yeah we're here
along for the ride and we're really
enjoying it and learning a lot learning
a lot from a lot of these mobile app
companies awesome well it's been really
fun chatting through this with you and
and I'm similarly excited about what
we'll see continue to grow and change on
uh Web building for apps anything else
you wanted to share as we wrap up we're
going to include links to your personal
LinkedIn in and to paddle of course but
anything else you wanted to share as we
wrapped up no I think you're good thanks
for having me on as you just mentioned
very happy for people to reach out to me
via the typical channels LinkedIn X
Twitter whatever we call it these days
but yeah thanks very much for having me
on David it's been it's been a great
conversation thanks so much for
listening if you have a minute please
leave a review on your favorite podcast
player you can also stop by chat. sub
club.com to join our private community
[Music]